Revere, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1828-1963.
Congregational Library & Archives
Revere, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1828-1963.
RG0149
Congregational Library & Archives
1.53 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
In 1828, a group gathered in the home of Joseph Harris to form a new church called the Evangelical Congregational Society of Chelsea. They wanted a new place to worship as the church in Rumney Marsh had moved toward Unitarianism. In 1898, the church became a corporation and changed its name to the First Congregational Church of Revere, taking over the property and debts of the First Evangelical Congregational Society of Revere. A variety of different ministers would lead for short periods until Rev. E. Ambrose Jenkins took over in 1923 and served for 21 years. Rev. Jenkins passed away in 1944 and would be followed up by his assistant, Rev. Lloyd F. Dean. A parsonage fund was formed that same year and resulted in the purchase of a home in 1950. The church continued to thrive into the 21st century and is still open as of 2021, led by Reverend Timothy Bogertman. This collection contains church records, pew deeds, standing committee meetings, church calendars, deeds, mortgages, bequests, real estate papers, loans, and land agreements.
First Congregational Church (Revere, Mass.)
Evangelical Congregational Society of North Chelsea (North Chelsea, Mass.)
Evangelical Congregational Church (Rumney Marsh, Chelsea, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information is available for this collection.
Historical Information
The origin of the church begins in 1709 in the area then known as Rumney Marsh. Boston selectmen approved a payment of 50 pounds to be used for purchasing land for a meetinghouse. This church started out with Orthodox beliefs but over the next hundred years moved toward Unitarianism. This move culminated on March 27th, 1828 when a group of members gathered in the home of Joseph Harris in order to form a new church called the Evangelical Congregational Society of Chelsea. The group formally requested dismission from the original church but was rejected.
After this rejection, the group decided to build a place of worship anyway and stayed there until 1842 when a new Congregational Church was formed in Chelsea. Worship would not continue in that building again until 1847, now under Reverend Noah Coe. In 1849, the group had grown to the point where a new church was required. This new building was completed in December and its dedication service was in January 1850.
The church encountered financial woes for some time after this, but by 1875 they had become much more stable. Reverend Joseph Bixby became the pastor in 1879, following in a line of over 20 different ministers since the church was founded. In 1883, the church began admitting women into the society as full members.
Reverend Walter Eaton would become the minister in 1892. In 1898, the church became a corporation and changed its name to the First Congregational Church of Revere, taking over the property and debts of the First Evangelical Congregational Society of Revere. Rev. Eaton would leave in September 1903 and from here the list of ministers would go through constant change for some time. The list starts with Dr. Houghton, who stayed on in a temporary fashion before the arrival of Rev. John Holmes in November 1903. Next would be Rev. Howard L. Torbet in 1909 and then Rev. R.J. Elliot in 1914. Rev. Edville A. Roys joined for a short stay in 1918 and would be replaced in the same year by Rev. Stephen James. James would lead the community into joining the Methodist Church, but this would only last until May of 1919. At this time, Rev. Ermil Frye would become minister and then Rev. E. Ambrose Jenkins would take over for him in 1923. Rev. Jenkins would remain for 21 years, providing some stability for the church. Rev. Jenkins passed away in 1944 and would be followed up by his assistant, Rev. Lloyd F. Dean, though he was not officially ordained until 1946. A parsonage fund was formed that same year and resulted in the purchase of a home in 1950. Rev. Dean would move on in September of 1950 and would be replaced by Rev. Donald Tatro.
The church continued to thrive into the 21st century and is still open today. They joined the Conservative Congregational Christian Conference and as of July 2021 are led by Reverend Timothy Bogertman.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains church records, pew deeds, standing committee meetings, church calendars, deeds, mortgages, bequests, real estate papers, loans, and land agreements.
Arrangement
This collection is divided into two series. Records in each series are arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Church records, 1828-1934
Series 2: Financial information, 1853-1963
Bibliography
Pearson, Martha G. "The History of the First Congregational Church of Revere" Paper presented at the 125th Anniversary, Revere, MA, May 1953.
Church records and registers.; Church buildings; Church finance.; Vital statistics.; Pews and pew rights.; Church property.; First Congregational Church (Revere, Mass.); Evangelical Congregational Society of North Chelsea (North Chelsea, Mass.); Evangelical Congregational Church (Rumney Marsh, Chelsea, Mass.)
- Church records, 1828 1934; 1828-1934; 8 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains church records, pew deeds, standing committee meetings and some church calendars.
  - Church records, 1828 1884; 1828-1884 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Church records, 1828 1898; 1828-1898 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Church register, 1842 1920; 1842-1920 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Pew Deeds, 1850 1867; 1850-1867 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Church calendar, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Church records, 1885-05 1911-01; May 1885-January 1911 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Church records, 1911 1931; 1911-1931 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Standing committee meeting minutes, 1926 1934; 1926-1934 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Financial information, 1853 1963; 1853-1963; 24 Folders
  This series contains financial information related to deeds, mortgages, bequests, real estate papers, loans, and land agreements.
  - Notice of Deed and Mortgage, 1853-10-01 1853-10-31; October 1853 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Organization, March 21, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Property Transfer, April 8, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Property Transfer, March 6, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Discharge of Mortgages, February 9, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Grant Mortgage, February 14. 1935 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Loan Mortgage, 1935 1939; 1935-1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Satisfaction of Morgages, 1935 1948; 1935-1938, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bequest of First Congregational Church, April 6, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Board of Home Missions loan instructions, November 20, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Application for Loan on Church building, December 17, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certificate of Completion of House of Worship, 1938 1939; 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Quitclaim Deed, June 14, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Board of Home Missions receipt, May 7, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate agreement, 1950-08-01 1950-08-31; August 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Quitclaim Deed, 1950-09 1950-11; September-November 1950 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Assignment of Interest, October 20, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Payments to Chelsea Savings Bank, 1950 1963; 1950, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Mortgage Payments, 1950 1951; 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Certificate of Title, July 1, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Copy of Land Court Agreement, October 18, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Discharge of Mortgage, April 4, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Grant from Massachusetts Congregational Conference and Missionary Society, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Application for Loan on Church building, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)